Guide to the Isaac Hicks Papers 1791-1820 MS 297
New-York Historical Society
- Series I: Correspondence, 1791-1806; 18 Linear feet
  - Letters: 1799 I-R (Box -)
    - Letters: R (Except Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan; Rodman; Rotch), 1799 (Box 14, Folder 10)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Nathaniel Ray, Daniel Ricketson, John Robinson & Sons, and James Rocquette & Sons. Nathaniel Ray discusses what to do with his proceeds should the ship Nancy be sold for salvage. Daniel Ricketson discusses the sale of the ship Franklin. William Robertson discusses speculation in the American market. James Rocquette & Sons discuss fluctuating prices of a number of goods including cotton and tobacco. He also discusses his hesitancy in sending goods due to an outbreak of a 'sickness.'
      Ships Mentioned: Nancy, Franklin
    - Letters: Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan, 1799 (Box 14, Folder 11)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from the house Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan. The correspondence is primarily in regards to the sale and shipment of goods-especially tobacco and cotton.
      Ships Mentioned: Pearl, Elizabeth, Perseverance, Cleopatra, Peggy
    - Letters: Rodman, Joseph; Rodman, Samuel, 1799 (Box 14, Folder 12)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Joseph Rodman of Charleston, South Carolina, and Samuel Rodman of New Bedford, Massachusetts. Joseph Rodman writes predominantly about the shipment of goods-especially rice. Samuel Rodman writes predominantly about the sale and shipment of whale products such as spermaceti candles and sperm oil
      Ships Mentioned: Pasha, Sally, Prudence, Diana, Lydia
    - Letters: Rotch, William, 1799 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Letters: 1799 S-Z (Box -)
    - Letters: S (Except Shearman; Shepherd; Smith, George; Spear; Swain), 1799 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      This folder incudes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including John Shaw, David Sherman, and Elijah Smith. John Shaw asks Hicks to procure insurance for the brig Rachel. David Sherman discusses his voyages, and relations with other captains. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Rachel, Orange, Janus
    - Letters: Shearman; Shepherd, 1799 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from individuals with the surname Shearman and Shepherd-predominantly Isaac Shearman and Allen Shepherd. One letter asks Hicks to handle all mail and goods sent to John Shearman and forward it to him in Newport. The remainder of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Polly, President, Nancy, Janus
    - Letters: Smith, George; Speare; Swain, 1799 (Box 15, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients George Smith from Hamburg, Germany; Robert Spear; and individuals with the surname Swain including Barnabas Swain and Isaiah Swain. George Smith predominantly discusses the sale and shipment of goods-especially coffee and sugar. He also discusses the falling prices of goods in Hamburg and laments the lack of circulating funds. Robert Spear expresses his anxiety that his letters had not been received. He also talks extensively about the sale and shipment of cotton. There are multiple duplicate letters from Robert Spear.
      Ships Mentioned: Minerva, Mary, Brilliant, Montezuma, Betsey, Union
    - Letters: T-V, 1799 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Sandford Taber, Elkanah Tallman, Thomas Tennison, Thornton & Power, and Lemuel Tripp. Sandford Taber discusses one of his voyages including where he went and the weather on the voyage. Thornton & Power discusses the varying prices of goods such as tobacco, coffee and sugar. Lemuel Tripp explains an issue he had aboard the ship Franklin, saying that the captain had "abused me shamefully". A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters-especially the sale and shipment of goods, and the payment of debts.
    - Letters: W-Z, 1799 (Box 15, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including George Warrick, Stephen Waterman, John Watkins, Gid Hill Wells, John Welsh, Joseph Whelden, Wilkinson & Borlano, and Cornelius Wing. David Webb discusses how he can no longer go to sea during the winter season because his wife is gravely ill and suggested another individual to go in his place. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the sale and shipment of goods, as well as the payment of debts.
      Ships Mentioned: Hope, Elizabeth, Liberty, Suffolk, Perseverance, Franklin
  - Letters: 1800 A-D (Box -)
    - Letters: A, 1800 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      This folder contains correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including William Anderson, Gideon Alden, James Andrews, Joseph Anthony & Co., and Anthony & Pleasants. Anderson discusses growing tensions between the United States and Great Britain as war in Europe continues. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the sale and purchase of goods such as tobacco.
    - Letters: B (Except Barker; Bolton), 1800 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Henry Barnard; Beddermaker & Co.; Thomas Bell; Robert Benson; John Berenberg, Gossler & Co.; and Sam Blain. Wilson Barstow discusses the potential sale of the sloop Eliza. Beddermaker & Co. discuss the increasing sales of coffee. A majority of the correspondence is in regard to the sale of goods.
      Ships Mentioned: Oswego, Betsey, Eliza, Albion
    - Letters: Bolton, Robert & John (1), 1800 (Box 16, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from Curtis, Robert, and John Bolton. Main topics include the sale and shipment of goods such as cotton and tobacco, as well as the payment of debts.
      Ships Mentioned: Rachel, Concord, Nixon, George, Mercer, Diana, President
    - Letters: Bolton, Robert & John (2), 1800 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from Robert & John Bolton. Main topics include the sale and shipment of goods-especially cotton, the payment of bills, and the procurement of ships for the transportation of goods.
      Ships Mentioned: Nixon, Debbie, Recourse, Eliza, Nabby, General Mercer
    - Letters: Barker, Jacob, 1800 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from Jacob Barker. Barker discusses how he was unable to find lodgings after a long voyage. Most of the correspondence is in regard to procuring ships for trade, and the sale of goods.
      Ships Mentioned: Venus
    - Letters: C (Except Coffin; Cropper & Benson), 1800 (Box 16, Folder 6)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including David Callaghan, B. Cartwright, Dennis Cauldfield, Alex & Benjamin Champion, Richard Chad, D. Coleman, and Cope & Brothers. Main topics include the sale of goods such as wheat, ashes, cotton, tobacco, and staves.
      Ships Mentioned: General Mercer, Favourite, Eliza
    - Letters: Coffin, 1800 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from individuals with the surname Coffin, including Abner Coffin, Alex Coffin, Isaac Coffin, and Micajah Coffin. Included is a list of debits and credits and inventories of Alex Coffin. Much of the correspondence is in regards to the payment of bills, but also includes letters regarding the procurement of insurance
      Ships Mentioned: General Mercer, Minerva, Lydia, Fortitude
    - Letters: Cropper & Benson, 1800 (Box 16, Folder 8)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Cropper & Benson. It includes prices current from Liverpool. They discuss the alarming shortage of corn for sale, as well as the importation of other goods such as wheat and flour. They also discuss the decreasing price of cotton and how they do not expect the price to increase in the near future. A majority of the correspondence discusses bills, payment of debts, and invoices.
      Ships Mentioned: Warren, Augusta, Canton, Fortitude
    - Letters: D (Except Deaves; Delano; Drinker), 1800 (Box 16, Folder 9)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Dawson & Watt, the Brothers Debaque, John Deering, Frederick Delius, George Dobson, and Elihu Doty. The Brothers Debaque discuss how they believe they are being defrauded by a Mr. Tones, Frederick Delius discusses mercantilism over the past year, how the river had just thawed, and the prices of coffee.
      Ships Mentioned: Rebecca, Juliana
    - Letters: Deaves, 1800 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from Henry Deaves and John Deaves. Main topics include the state of the markets, the shipment of goods, and the payment of bills.
      Ships Mentioned: Washington, Olive Branch, Amita, Susan, Osiris, Adventure
    - Letters: Delano, 1800 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from John Delano. Main topics include the sale and purchase of goods. The letters also discuss the shipment of goods, though no specific ships are mentioned.
    - Letters: Drinker, 1800 (Box 16, Folder 12)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client, Henry Drinker of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Main topics include the sale and shipment of goods, the payment of bills, and the procurement of insurance. Drinker reminds Hicks of a piece of advice stating "thou that had nothing to say would say nothing". He also discusses attending a quarterly meeting of "our boarding school", though he gives no indication regarding the name of the institution.
      Ships Mentioned: Brilliant
  - Letters: 1800 E-L (Box -)
    - Letters: E-F (Except Fisher; Forbes), 1800 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including S. Edmonds, Killey Eldridge, John Elkins, William English, William Field, Captain P. Fish, Thomas & Joshua Fisher, and Robert Folger. Main topics include the sale and shipment of goods and the payment of bills. Captain Fish discusses purchasing a ship equally between himself, Allen Shepherd, James Howland, and Cornelius Grinnell. Robert Folger discusses how the ship George was castaway off the coast of England, and how the second mate was lost. Folger also discusses having difficulty with the payout of an insurance claim.
      Ships Mentioned: Minerva, Juliana, Commerce, George, Favourite, Hercules
    - Letters: Fisher, Samuel & Miers, 1800 (Box 17, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Samuel & Miers Fisher of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the payment of bills and the sale and shipment of goods. They discuss how their family has been greatly affected by illness, and how two sons had passed away. They also discuss how multiple individuals are behind on payments due to them, and ask Hicks to take control over obtaining the funds.
    - Letters: Forbes, Edward, 1800 (Box 17, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client Edward Forbes of Dublin, Ireland. Forbes laments how Mr. Clear stated that the staves sent from New York were the worst quality he had ever seen, and the worst of other ships from New York as well. He suggests that Marshall Jenkins & Son should not have switched houses until they paid off their debt. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the shipment of goods and the payment of debts. There are multiple copies of multiple letters included in this folder.
      Ships Mentioned: Fortitude, Fame, Eliza, Revolution
    - Letters: G, 1800 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Albert Gardner, Gideon Gardner, Laban Gardner, Paul Gardner & Sons, Gardner & Mitchell, Samuel Ghaskill, Robert Gill, Benjamin Glover, and Moses Grant. A majority of the correspondence is in regard to the sale and shipment of goods, as well as the procurement of insurance policies. Included is an invoice for ½ of a case of cotton goods sent to Hicks.
      Ships Mentioned: Commerce, Laura, Magnet
    - Letters: H (Except Harvey, Deaves, & Harvey; Harvey & Lecky; Thomas Hazard; Howland; Hussey), 1800 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Robert Hamilton, Daniel Hart, Harvey & Fisher, Frank Harvey, Rowland Hazard, Giles Hosier & Son, Benjamin Huntting, and Peleg Huttlestone. Main topics include the sale and shipment of goods such as staves, ashes, and cotton. Benjamin Huntting asks Hicks to find a "Molatto pitted with small pox" who was supposed to board a ship but did not.
      Ships Mentioned: Sarah, America
    - Letters: Harvey, Deaves, & Harvey; Harvey & Lecky, 1800 (Box 17, Folder 6)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Harvey, Deaves, & Harvey, and Harvey & Lecky. Harvey, Deaves, & Harvey talk a lot about the ship Olive Branch and her voyages and cargo. Harvey & Lecky predominantly discuss payment of bills and other accounting matters. They also ask Hicks to assist an associate of theirs, Thomas Goin, in starting in the chandlery & soap business.
      Ships Mentioned: Olive Branch, Oswego, Minerva
    - Letters: Hazard, Thomas; Howland; Hussey, 1800 (Box 17, Folder 7)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from Thomas Hazard and individuals with the surnames Howland and Hussey including Isaac Howland & sons, John Howland, George Hussey. Thomas Hazard discusses the purchase and sale of goods such as candles, oil, coffee, and sugar. He also acknowledges that Hicks is beginning to move away from the commission of whale products back to the commission of dry goods in general. Included is a letter stating how the ship Commerce would need repairs before she could return to the United States. Isaac Howland & Sons discusses with Hicks that because he could not settle his debts with Isaac Roget, they could not settle with others-they later ask Hicks to sue Roget for the debt that he owes.
      Ships Mentioned: Sarah, Commerce, Polly, Hope, Sukey, Franklin, Lucretia, Mars, Renwick, Mary
    - Letters: J (Except Jenkins, Jonathan), 1800 (Box 17, Folder 8)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including James, Gibbon, & English, Elisha & Gilbert Jenkins, Robert Jenkins & Co., Thomas Jenkins & Sons, Ruben Jenne, and E. Jones. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the sale and shipment of goods, procurement of insurance and receiving payments. Also included is an accounting page from the ship Columbia. Ships Mentioned: Fortitude, General Mercer, Canton
    - Letters: Jenkins, Jonathan, 1800 (Box 17, Folder 9)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from Jonathan Jenkins of Nantucket, Massachusetts. The correspondence is primarily in regards to the sale and shipping of whale products.
      Ships Mentioned: Betsey
    - Letters: K-L, 1800 (Box 17, Folder 10)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Joseph King, James & Thomas Lamb, George Langhy, Paul Lanuise, and Thomas Lorian. Knox & Nay discuss the poor condition of cotton that they received and William Lamb asks for books to be shipped. Most of the correspondence is in regard to the sale and shipment of goods such as tobacco. Samuel Lord expresses how his son will settle his bill next month when he was in town. Other letters are mostly asking Hicks to send goods or informing Hicks that goods had been sent. There are also letters in French from Paul Lanuise.
      Ships Mentioned: Nancy, Iris, Polly, Favorite Patsy
  - Letters: 1800 M-R (Box -)
    - Letters: M (Except Mark, Jacob; O & A Mitchell; Moores), 1800 (Box 18, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including George McConnell, Seth Macy, Ruben Mason, J & W Mellish & Co., Morgan & Douglass, and Joseph Morris. J&W Mellish & Co discuss how British Parliament is attempting to encourage the importation of wheat, flour, and rice. A majority of the correspondence is in regard to the sale and shipment of goods.
      Ships Mentioned: Adventure, Warren, Olive Branch, Commerce, Sally
    - Letters: Mark, Jacob; Mitchell, O. & A.; Moores, Ruben, 1800 (Box 18, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from Jacob Mark, O & A Mitchell, and Ruben Moores. His correspondence with Jacob Mark is predominantly regarding the sale and shipment of sea island cotton and other goods. He also discusses the payment of bills. O & A Mitchell discusses insurance policies and payments thereof. They also ask Hicks about why his language was negative in a previous letter. Ruben Moores discusses the shipment of wine and other goods as well as the payment of bills. There is also a contract between Moores and Thomas Hazard regarding Hazard taking control of the ship Sarah.
      Ships Mentioned: Superior, Daphne, Active, Hercules, Hope, Nancy, Sarah
    - Letters: N-O, 1800 (Box 18, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Samuel Norton, David Ogden, and George Otis. Sam Norton discusses insurance policies on multiple ships. He also discusses the sale of cargo. Ogden discusses an insurance payout that Hicks owes. Otis continues a conversation that began when he was visiting New York.
      Ships Mentioned: Eliza, Fortitude, Cleopatra, Polly
    - Letters: P (Except Prudhomme), 1800 (Box 18, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Judah Paddock, Laban Paddock, Jonathan Parker, Thaddeus Pickens, Andrew Pinkham, J. Piper, and Peter Pollard. Judah Paddock informs Hicks that recently "French privateers have been boarding American vessels and letting them pass, particularly those that are unarmed", and discusses the procurement of insurance. J. Piper discusses the continuance of a "mortal disease" in the Fells Point neighborhood of Baltimore.
      Ships Mentioned: Oswego, Constellation, President, Prudence, Hope
    - Letters: Prudhomme, 1800 (Box 18, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client Lewis Prudhomme of Washington, D.C. Main topics include the declining price of cotton, the sale and shipment of cotton and tobacco, and the procurement of goods.
    - Letters: R (Except Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan; Rocquette, Beeldeaker & G; Rodman; Rotch) (Box 18, Folder 6)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Abel Rawson, Boyd Reid, Thomas Rhodes, and John Robinson & Sons. Thomas Rhodes requests information regarding the quality and price of rice. There is a letter introducing Hicks to the new house Richardson, Timmins, & Mendham. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the sale and shipment of goods such as cotton and rice. Also included is an inventory and price list from John Robinson & Sons.
      Ships Mentioned: Mary Pollard, Lucinda, Sarah, General Mercer
    - Letters: Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan (1), 1800 (Box 18, Folder 7)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan. They express concerns to changes to the American export situation. They also discuss the changing price of flour, wheat, and rice. Also included is an order from the House of Commons of Great Britain regulating the sale of wheat and wheat products, and imposing tariffs. There is also mention of debit sheets, but none are included.
      Ships Mentioned: Perseverance, Charlestown, Hare, General Mercer, Catherine, Fortitude
    - Letters: Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan (2), 1800 (Box 18, Folder 8)
      Scope and Contents
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan. They discuss the continuing tariffs on flour. They also discuss the wreck of the ship Oswego, as well as relaying the statuses of multiple other vessels. They write to Hicks that they will be sending invoices and bills of lading in multiple letters. They also discuss an embargo on British vessels placed by the Russian Emperor.
      Ships Mentioned: Nancy, Swift, Oswego, President, Nixon, Diana, Perseverance, General Mercer, Charlestown, Fortitude
    - Letters: Rocquette, Beeldemaker & Co.; Rodman, Joseph; Rotch, Thomas, 1800 (Box 18, Folder 9)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Rocquette, Beeldemaker, & Co.; Joseph Rodman; and Thomas Rotch. Rocquette, Beeldemaker, & Co. discuss the state of their markets, including the scarcity of coffee, sugar, and tobacco. Joseph Rodman predominantly discusses the payment of debts. He also discusses a possible peace between England, France, and Spain. Thomas Rotch mostly discusses the sale and shipment of goods such as whale oil.
      Ships Mentioned: Rising Sun, Delight, Bonaventure, Sarah, Diana, Maria, Eliza, Hope
  - Letters: 1800 S-W (Box -)
    - Letters: S (Except Speare), 1800 (Box 19, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Ezra Sampson, Shanahan Smith, J. Shearman, Isaac Shearman, Allen Shepherd, and George Smith & Co. Hester Sands asks Hicks to send him and cousin Phebe some fresh fish because they have had poor appetites and have been ill. A majority of the correspondence is in regard to the sale and shipment of goods such as linens, cotton, and tobacco. J. Shearman asks Hicks if he owes a captain a portion of the profits on a sale of goods, or if it is acceptable to just pay him the balance due. Other correspondence is in regards to the payment of bills.
      Ships Mentioned: Rowena, Polly, Enterprise, Columbia, Betsy
    - Letters: Speare, Robert, 1800 (Box 19, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client Robert Speare. The correspondence is mainly in regards to regular business matters and primarily focuses on the shipment of goods and the settling of accounts.
    - Letters: T, 1800 (Box 19, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Sanford Tabor, Drury Thompson, and Thornton & Power. Sanford Tabor discusses being quarantined on the ship he was traveling on due to the fact that there was a sick man on board. He expresses how he will not be allowed off of the vessel until approval was given by the health commissioner. The remainder of the correspondence is predominantly in regards to the sale of goods.
      Ships Mentioned: Daphne
    - Letters: W, 1800 (Box 19, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Josiah Wade, John Waring, A. Weisheinel, Peter West, George Williams, Roger Wing, and David Worth. The correspondence is mainly in regards to regular business matters—primarily the sale and shipment of goods.
      Ships Mentioned: Lucretia, Lucinda, George
  - Letters: 1801 A-C (Box -)
    - Letters: A, 1801 (Box 20, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including John Alden, and Anthony & Pleasant. Multiple letters mention the death of an associate of Hicks, Mr. Francisco Antonio deCastro, who left Hicks his business. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the sale and shipment of goods. There are letters included in Spanish.
      Ships Mentioned: Eagle, Commerce
    - Letters: B (Except Barker; Bolton; Bunker), 1801 (Box 20, Folder 2)